Email: jamal.emc@gmail.com

House No. 410, Street No. 59,

G-10/4, Islamabad, Pakistan.

Jamal ud Din Qureshi
(Environmentalist)

Objective

Contact: +923214521413

To seek a dynamic career in a renowned organization where I can utilize my capabilities for excellence and sublime professional skills regarding my education and experience and which also provides opportunities for Research, Development and Remedial Measures related to Environmental Issues.

#### Education

#### MS in Environmental Sciences, University of the Punjab, Lahore, 2008.

Thesis Title: Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) of Proposed Commercial Building, Lahore.

# BS (Hons) in Environmental Sciences, University of the Punjab, Lahore, 2006.

Thesis Title: Evaluation of Occupational Health & Safety Issues in FMC Pesticides Formulation Plant, Lahore.

#### **Background**

Over 7 years of experience in Management systems (EIA/IEE's, EMMP's, Environment, Social, Energy and Health & Safety, EMS). Collaborated as an Individual Consultant with International Funded organizations; USAID, Chemonics International Inc., United Nations, providing Consultancy services on Relevant Projects. Providing consultancy/Advisory services in the field of Environmental Impacts Assessment (EIA) & Initial Environmental Examination (IEE) to local and multinational organizations; Environmental Management Consultants (EMC), & Sustainable Business Solutions (SBS).

Including 5 years teaching experience of EIA/IEE, EMS, OH&S, Pollution Control Technologies, Energy & Environment, Alternate Energy Resources, Health & Environment, Environmental & Natural Resource Economics, at International Islamic University, University of the Punjab, Lahore, & Bahria University, Islamabad. I have also supervised research thesis/projects in the field of Environmental Sciences in the said Universities.

#### Work Experience

i. Lecturer at International Islamic University, Islamabad at Department of Environmental Sciences, Faculty of Basic & Applied Sciences (FBAS).

4<sup>th</sup> Oct, 2010-Present

Teaching relevant subjects in the field of Environmental Sciences; EIA/IEE, EMS, OH&S, Pollution Control Technologies, Energy & Environment, Alternate Energy Resources, Health & Environment, Environmental & Natural Resource Economics, at BS (Hons) and MS level at International Islamic University, Islamabad.

Have Supervised Thesis/Project reports at BS (Hons) level at various Universities; International Islamic University, Islamabad, University of the Punjab, Lahore and Bahria University, Islamabad.

ii. Environmental Consultant at United States Agency for International Development (USAID) Firms Project; implemented by Chemonics International Inc, Lahore.

30 th Sep. 2013 to 30 th Apr 2014

To develop the Initial Environmental Examination (IEE) Reports of one Dried Mango Unit, six Fresh Mango Infrastructure Agreement and one Fruit and Vegetable Pulping Unit and obtain a No Objection Certificate (NoC) from the Sindh Environmental Protection Agency (Sindh EPA) situated in Karachi, for the USAID Firm's Project Dried Mango, Fresh Mango and Fruit & Vegetable Pulping Sector.

iii. Environmental Consultant at United States Agency for International Development (USAID) Firms Project; implemented by Chemonics International Inc, Lahore.

25<sup>th</sup> Jun, 2014 to 29<sup>th</sup> Aug, 2014

To develop Initial Environmental Examination (IEE) reports for eight Marble & Granite Units situated at Islamabad Peshawar, Charsadda, and Muridke.

iv. Environmental Specialist at Environmental Management Consultants (EMC), Lahore-Karachi.

22 Sep. 2007 to Jun, 2010

Preparation of Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) & Initial Environmental Examination (IEE). To conduct Environmental Audits (Site Audit, Compliance Audits, EMS Audits, and OH&S Audits) Preparation of Technical reports, Site visits. Coordination with the client and Government for issuance of NOC's.

#### Projects Completed

Sr. No	Title of Project	Client	Company	Year
1.	Development of IEE Reports for Eight Marble & Granite Sector located at Islamabad, Punjab & KPK.	USAID Firms Project	Chemonics International Inc.	2014
2.	Development of Feasibility Study for the implementation of better electricity appliances in major cities of Pakistan (Islamabad, Karachi, Lahore) for Energy Conservation.	NIPON KOEI & JICA	Research & Development (R&D)	2014
3.	Development of Initial Environmental Examination (IEE) for the construction of Integrated Resource Recovery Centre (IRRC) in Sector G-15, Islamabad-Pakistan.	UNHABITAT	EMC	2014
4.	Development of IEE Reports for Nine Mango Units and Obtain NOC from Sindh EPA for Dried Mango, Fresh Mango and Fruit and Vegetable Pulping Units.	USAID Firms Project	Chemonics International Inc.	2013-2014

5.	Base line study for Solid Waste Management in	UNHABITAT	EMC	2013
6.	Islamabad (I-9,I-10 Sectors)  Initial Environmental Examination (IEE) for National Poultry Control Shed Attock, Punjab.	Qadeer Brothers	SBS	2013
7.	Initial Environmental Examination (IEE) for Pak Packages, Sundar Industrial Estate, Lahore.	Pak Packages	UEC	2013
8.	Initial Environmental Examination (IEE) of Capacity Enhancement Project of Phillip Morris (Pakistan) Limited, Sahiwal Unit, Punjab.	Phillip Morris	EMC	2012
9.	Environmental Impact Assessment Study of Shaheed Benazir Bhutto Bridge over River Indus Connecting Chahchran Sharif to Mithan Kot, Punjab.	National Highway Authority (NHA)	EMC	2012
10.	Environmental Impact Assessment of Fateh Jang Oil & Gas Exploration sites, Punjab.	Oil & Gas Development Company Limited	EMC	2011
11.	Environmental Impact Assessment of Dakhni Oil & Gas Exploration sites, Punjab.	Oil & Gas Development Company Limited	EMC	2011
12.	Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) of Pan Power International Pvt. Ltd. Sundar Industrial Estate, Lahore.	PIIL	SMIS	2010
13.	Initial environmental examination of ASKAR diesel oil storage facility, Mouza Sundar Lahore-Multan. Road, district Lahore.	ASKAR	UEC	2010
14.	Initial Environmental Examination (IEE) for up- gradation of Naudero Rental Power Plant 50-51MW (101MW), Naudero -Sindh.	Walter Power International	EMC	2010
15.	Initial Environmental Examination (IEE) for the construction of Warehouse (Organic Storage facility) Karachi.		EMC	2010
16.	Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) of PAN Islamic Industries Private Limited, Sundar Industrial Estate, Lahore.	PIIL	SMIS	2010
17.	Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) of Nazir Paper & Board Mill, Sundar Industrial Estate, Lahore.	Nazir Paper Mill	UEC	2010

18.	Site Surveys in Khipro Block (Sindh) to identify the environmental & health impacts from produced water evaporation ponds due to Oil & Gas Exploration.	BP (British Petroleum)	EMC	2010
19.	Nationwide Mapping of the Textile Industries to analyze the requirements of Treatment Plant, with the Co-ordination of Ministry of Textiles (MINTEX), Government of Pakistan.	Ministry of Textiles (MINTEX), Government of Pakistan	EMC	2009-10
20.	InitialEnvironmental Examination forthe Construction of multi-use complex namely DIVINE MEGA 2 at Main Defense Road, Lahore.	DIVINE	EMC	2009-10
21.	Environmental Assessment Power Plant & CRM at Landhi, Karachi.	International Industries Ltd	EMC	2008
22.	Environmental, Health & Safety (EHS) Audit at RECKITT & BENCKSER Plant Multan Road, Lahore.	RECKITT & BENCKSER	EMC	2008
23.	Initial Environmental Examination of Services Apartments, Lahore.	ORIX	EMC	2007-08
24.	Environmental Impact Assessment of Mabarak Centre, Lahore.	TAAVUN, TURNER International, Govt. of Punjab	EMC	2007

#### Conferences/ Workshops Attended

- 1. HABC LEVEL 2 AWARD IN FIRE SAFETY (QCF) organized by Sustainable Business Solutions (SBS), Lahore on September 13, 2013.
- International Workshop on Marine Biology-Ecology and Applications, Advancements and Issues of St
   Century. Organized by COMSTECH, Islamabad, in Collaboration with National Institute of Oceanography, Karachi-Pakistan, June 26-28, 2012.
- 3. SAARC Workshop on Science & Technology Issues on Climate Change. COMSTECH SECRETARIATE, Islamabad. 21-22 March, 2011.
- 4. Environmental Impact Assessment by Punjab Environment Ministry, Lahore, Pakistan, January 2007.
- 5. Environmental Management System (ISO 14001:2004) By SWISO International Certification Services CH-5610 Wohlen, Switzerland, Lahore, Pakistan, October 2005.
- 6. Waste Management as a mean of resource protection by College of Earth and Environmental Sciences, University of the Punjab, Lahore, Pakistan, March 2005.
- 7. Solid Waste Management by College of Earth and Environmental Sciences, University of the Punjab, Lahore, Pakistan, May 2005.

## Internships/ Trainings

Sr. No	Department/Institution/Company	Title	Year
1.	City District Government, Lahore (CDGL) Town	Internee	Jan-Dec 2008
	Department of Environment.		
2.	United Nations Office for Project Services	Internee	Jan-Feb 2007
	Islamabad		
3.	FMC, United (Food Machinery Chemicals) Lahore.	Internee	Aug- Sep 2005

### References

Will be provided on Request.